<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0"
          xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/changes/1.0.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/changes-1.0.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Change Report</title>
    <author email="zcarioca@zcarioca.net">zcarioca</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release date="2010-08-22" version="1.0" description="First Release">
      <action date="2010-08-22" dev="zcarioca" type="add">
        Cut the first official release.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release date="2013-xx-xx" version="1.5" description="Release 1.5">
      <action date="2012-01-26" dev="zcarioca" type="add">
        Added a PropertiesBuilder in place of Configuration object. This allows the user to specify properties in any order
        and still allows for keyword swapping.
      </action>
      <action date="2012-01-26" dev="zcarioca" type="fix">
        Removed the use of ExecutorServices and internal threading.  This will allow this library to be used with Application Servers 
        that prefer to manage their own threads. Instead the ConfigurationUtilities object has a "forceReconfigure" method that will
        reconfigure all of the beans associated to a given source.
      </action>
      <action date="2012-02-01" dev="zcarioca" type="add">
        Added a PropertiesBuilder factory to increase flexibility of library configurations.
      </action>
      <action date="2012-02-01" dev="zcarioca" type="update">
        Changed the logging framework to SLF4J. This removes the dependency on Log4J from the user.
      </action>
      <action date="2012-02-01" dev="zcarioca" type="remove">
        Removed unnecessary external dependencies.
      </action>
      <action date="2012-04-26" dev="zcarioca" type="update">
        Moved to Maven Central Repository in order to remove dependency on an additional repository.
      </action>
      <action date="2013-01-19" dev="zcarioca" type="update">
        Modified the ConfigurationSourceProviderFactory 'discover' the optimal provider for a ConfigurationSourceItentifier.
      </action>
      <action date="2013-01-20" dev="zcarioca" type="update">
        Modified the ConfigurationSourceProvider to determine priority so that providers may override each other when necessary.
      </action>
      <action date="2013-01-22" dev="zcarioca" type="add">
        Added the BeanPropertyConverter and BeanPropertyConverterRegistry to allow developers to create their own converters.
      </action>
      <action date="2013-01-23" dev="zcarioca" type="add">
        Added the ConfigurableDateFormat to allow configuration of Date and Calendar objects
      </action>
      <action date="2013-01-23" dev="zcarioca" type="add">
        Added the ConfigurableNumberFormat to allow number to be represented in properties files in binary, octal, decimal, or hexidecimal.
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
